# Michelle Jonika

#### BIOINFORMATICIAN · COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGIST · MOLECULAR GENETICIST

4225 Pendleton Dr. Apt. 7104 Bryan, TX, 77802, USA

🛮 (281)-825-9621 | 🗷 michellemjonika@gmail.com | 🏕 michellejonika@github.io | 🖸 michellejonika | 🛅 michellejonika

## Summary.

As a computational biologist, I enjoy the puzzle-like nature of coding genetics and genomics problems, specifically bringing this approach to the evolution of genomic content and sex chromosomes. Detail-oriented planning, project management, experimental design, and clear communication are important to my critical thinking and problem solving strategies for research. I am pursuing a Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics at Texas A&M University, and I defended my dissertation in January 2023 with a graduation date of May 2023. I am interested in career paths in industry intersecting bioinformatics, computational biology, genetics, genomics, and molecular biology.

## **Expertise**

Genomics: NGS Analysis and Pipeline Development (SRA, Trimmomatic, bwa, samtools, GATK), Genome Assembly (HiFiasm,

QUAST, BUSCO, BlobToolKit), RNASeq (FastQC, bowtie2, DESeq2), GWAS (PLINK, GEMMA), Genomic Prediction (rrBLUP)

**Genetics:** Evolutionary Biology (Genome structure evolution, Mammalian Sex chromosome evolution, Morphometrics),

Veterinary Medicine (Clinical Data Evaluation, Cancer Prediction), Crop Science (Epistasis, Introgression)

**Molecular Biology:** Primer optimization, gDNA/DNA extraction, RNA extraction, PCR, qPCR, Gel visualization/imaging, Flow Cytometry

**Chemistry:** GC-MS, DART-MS, Drug Database Design, LC-MS

**Programming:** R, Linux/Unix, tidyverse, Python, LaTeX, HTML/CSS, R Shiny

**Code Management:** Git/GitHub, VSCode, BitBucket, Docker, JIRA, conda

**Data Science:** Large dataset management (>20Gb), Machine Learning, Bayesian statistics, Phylogenetics, Simulations, Data

Visualization, Software Development, Amazon Web Services (AWS)/Cloud Computing, HPC Cluster Computing Project management, Public Speaking and Communication, Leadership, Multi-disciplinary Collaboration, Adaptive

**Soft Skills:** problem solving, Multi-tasking, Self-Motivated, Time Management, Strategic Planning

### Education

#### Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY | ADVISOR: HEATH BLACKMON

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

• Dissertation: Patterns and Processes in the Evolution of Sequence Classes and Genomic Compartments

### **B.S. in Forensic and Investigative Science**

College Station, Texas

Texas A&M University | Advisor: Aaron M. Tarone

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

• Thesis: Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology

# **Experience**

PetDx San Diego, California

BIOINFORMATICS INTERN | BIOINFORMATICS AND DATA SCIENCE TEAM

June 2022 - Aug. 2022

- Leveraged high-complexity data set to predict canine cancer types
- Used machine learning (Random Forest) approaches to train and evaluate different models
- · Performed extensive data evaluation to curate sample metrics, obtain balanced training and testing sets and identify meaningful model parameters

Bayer Crop Science St. Louis, Missouri

Data Science Intern | Genomics Discovery and Application Team

May 2021 - Aug. 2021

- Identifying historic data to test for epistasis and designing a follow-up experiment to test for epistasis
- Developing a statistical testing framework to identify interactions between introgressed loci
- Three-month, full-time position exposure in an industry setting
- · Establishing multi-disciplinary connections with teams with expertise in data science, genomics, and precision breeding

### Ph.D. Research | Advisor: Dr. Heath Blackmon

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M INTERDISCIPLINARY PROGRAM IN GENETICS AND GENOMICS | TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

- Developing an R package (Lo et al. 2019) to characterize microsatellite evolution and applying this package to characterize microsatellite evolution across 300 million years of insect evolution (Jonika et al. 2020)
- Elucidating the role of centromere type in insect chromosome evolution (Ruckman et al. 2020) and effective population size in carnivore chromosome evolution (Jonika et al. In Prep)
- Designing an automated genomic pipeline and TensorFlow based machine learning application to categorize genomic characteristics for 100s of mammalian species totaling 1000s of TB of genomic data

JULY 13, 2023 MICHELLE JONIKA · RÉSUMÉ 1

TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF ENTOMOLOGY

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

- Completed additional experimentation and formal writing from undergraduate thesis project (Jonika et al. 2020)
- · Applied new sex determination methodology and primer optimization to additional applications in forensic entomology (Pimsler et al. 2021) and stem cell research (Pitonak et al. 2022)

# **Teaching & Mentorship**

### **Teaching Assistant**

DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY | DEPARTMENT OF GENETICS

- Python for Biologists | Spring 2023 | Texas A&M
- Anatomy and Physiology | Spring 2022 | Texas A&M
- Critical Writing in Biology | Fall 2020, Spring 2021 | Texas A&M
- Introduction to Genetics Laboratory | Spring 2019, Spring 2023 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Forensic Genetics | Topic: Genetic Testing | Sep. 2022 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Bioinformatics | Topic: Genetic Privacy | Nov. 2021 | Utah Valley University

#### **Graduate Student Mentor**

**UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANTS** 

- Mentee: Johnathan Lo | Topic: Microsatellite Characterization and Evolution
- Mentee: Abhi Arekere | Topic: Carnivore Chromosome Number Evolution
- Mentee: Ragan Miller, Joseph Ward, Leen Fardoun | Topic: Chrysina Morphometrics

# **Leadership & Outreach**

### **Genetics Graduate Student Association**

PRESIDENT | VICE PRESIDENT | GRADUATE STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE | SEMINAR COMMITTEE

May 2019 - Current

- · Facilitate monthly graduate student association meetings
- · Oversee communication between current graduate students, genetics faculty, and the program executive committee

### **Texas A&M College of Science**

OUTREACH COMMITTEE | WOMEN IN SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Jan. 2019 - Current

- · Participated in various outreach activities important to the mission of the College of Science and Women in Science and Engineering
- · Served on the Women in Science and Engineering outreach committee and organized school STEM nights

### **Genetics Society of America**

EARLY CAREER LEADERSHIP PROGRAM - CAREER DEVELOPMENT SUBCOMMITTEE

Jan 2020 - Dec 2022

- Contribute career development blog pieces for Genes to Genomes blog
- · Curate resources contributing to a career development toolkit and early career researcher newsletters
- Organize career development workshops for bimonthly workshop series and TAGC conference

### **Awards & Grants**

JULY 13, 2023

- 2023 Texas A&M Distinguished Graduate Student Award, Texas A&M University
- 2023 Montgomery Award, Texas A&M University Graduate and Professional School
- 2023 Outstanding Ph.D. Student Presentation, Biology Department, Student PostDoc Research Conference
- Texas A&M Data Science Ambassador, Texas A&M University 2022
- Research Excellence Award, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program 2022

### Selected Publications

\*Please see Google Scholar for a full publications list

M. Pitonak, M. Aceves, P.A. Kumar, G. Dampf, P. Green, A. Tucker, V. Dietz, D. Miranda, S. Letchuman, M.M. Jonika, D. Bautista, H. Blackmon, J.N. Dulin. 2022. Effects of Biological Sex Mismatch on Neural ProgenitorCell Transplantation for Spinal Cord Injury in Mice. Nature Communications. 13(1):1-12.

M.M. Jonika, J.M. Alfieri, T. Sylvester, A.R. Buhrow, H. Blackmon. 2022. Why Not Y Naught. Heredity. 129. 75-78.

S. Ruckman\*(Co-first author), M.M. Jonika\*(Co-first author), C. Casola, H. Blackmon. 2020. Chromosome Number Evolves at Equal Rates in Holocentric and Monocentric Clades. PLOS Genetics 16(10):e1009076.

M.M. Jonika, C.E. Hjelmen, A.M. Faris, A.S. McGuane A.M. Tarone. 2020. An Evaluation of Differentially Spliced Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology. J. of Forensic Science 65(5): 1579-1587

J. Lo, M.M. Jonika, H. Blackmon. 2019. micRocounter: Microsatellite Characterization in Genome Assemblies. G3 9(10): 3101-3104

J.M. Alfieri, G. Wang, M.M. Jonika, C.A. Gill, G.N. Athrey, H. Blackmon. 2022. A Primer for Single-Cell Sequencing in Non-Model Organisms. Genes 13(2).

MICHELLE JONIKA · RÉSUMÉ